So one of the things that I want to try as we're talking about align-items and
من الأمور التي أريد اطلاعكم عليها فيما نتحدث عن محاذاة العناصر
justify content is how you can use documentation yourself.
وضبط المحتوى هي كيفية كتابة التعليمات البرمجية.
It's really impossible to memorize every single type of code there is.
من المستحيل حفظ كافة التعليمات البرمجية
Sure, you put your 10,000 hours in and you know a lot of the stuff by heart.
ولكن، بعد قضاء 10 آلاف ساعة في استخدامها، لا بد أن تحفظ العديد منها عن ظهر قلب
You pick it up, your fingers start to know the keystrokes.
ومع الوقت ستعتاد على كتابتها بسرعة.
But the truth is there's so many properties that even professional developers,
مع ذلك، ونظرًا لوجود العديد من الخصائص، نجد أن المطورون المحترفون يحتاجون
often consult the documentation to learn all of them.
للاطلاع على التعليمات البرمجية لمعرفة المزيد عنها.
So last night, as I was preparing this run through,
ليلة أمس، أثناء تحضيري للدرس
going through the documentation myself, I thought,
اطلعت على التعليمات البرمجية، وقررت
Instead of pretending I'm totally brilliant and just always know this stuff,
أنه بدلًا من التظاهر بالذكاء ومعرفة كل شيء دومًا،
I would show some of that process with you and we could share
أن استعرض معكم جزءًا من العملية
the process of looking at documentation as we're working with code.
ونطلع معًا على التعليمات البرمجية أثناء البرمجة.
So let's see how it goes.
لنرَ كيف يسير الأمر.
Here I'm looking at the justify-content page.
لدينا هنا صفحة ضبط المحتوى.
I can see that the different possibilities for justify-content,
يمكننا رؤية الخيارات المختلفة لضبط المحتوى،
are start, center, space between,
وهي البداية، توسيط، تباعد،
space around, and space evenly.
مسافات محيطة ومسافات متساوية.
So over here I can tell that I'm using justify-content center,
من هنا يمكننا معرفة أنني أستخدم توسيط لضبط المحتوى
let's try some of the other ones.
لنجرب خيارات أخرى.
What happens if I go justify-content start?
ماذا يحدث إذا عدلنا ضبط المحتوى إلى البداية؟
Boom. Did you see that?
بووم. أرأيتم هذا؟
All the boxes moved over so that they start where my starting access is.
انتقلت كافة المربعات إلى نقطة البداية
Should we see it again? There they go, back to center.
لنعيدها إلى مكانها ها هي تعود إلى الوسط مرة أخرى.
Let's take a look at another one.
لنلق نظرة على خيار آخر.
What would happen if we did space around? Did you see that?
ماذا سيحدث عند اختيار مسافات محيطة؟ أرأيتم هذا؟
Now, it evenly distributes that with space in between each of them.
توزعت بانتظام مع مسافات تفصل بينها وتحيط بها
Should we see it again? There it is, centered.
لنكرر الأمر هكذا تعود إلى الوسط.
Here it is, space around.
وهكذا مع مسافات محيطة.
Should we try one more?
لنجرب خيارًا آخر
How about space evenly?
هذه مسافات متساوية
Cool. These are only working, if you notice,
رائع. ربما لاحظتم أن خصائص الضبط تُستخدم
justify-content is doing things on the horizontal access.
فقط لضبط المحتوى على المحور الأفقي.
Let's try some different settings with aligned items.
لنجرب إعدادات مختلفة لمحاذاة العناصر
In order to do so, I'm going to create a few more boxes.
لفعل ذلك، سننشئ عددًا من المربعات الإضافية.
Okay. So now, let's take a look at aligning some items.
حسنًا. لنلق نظرة على محاذاة بعض العناصر
So we've added boxes four and five here,
أضفنا هنا المربعين أربعة وخمسة
so we can see boxes 1,
وأصبح لدينا مربع واحد
2, 3, 4, and 5.
اثنان، ثلاثة، أربعة وخمسة.
Here we can see that we have align item set to center.
نلاحظ أن محاذاة العناصر قد ضُبطت على توسيط
If we go into the documentation,
وإذا اطلعنا إلى التعليمات البرمجية
we can see that some of the other ones are stretch, start, and end.
سنجد بين الخصائص تمدد والبداية والنهاية.
So let's take a look at stretch.
لنلق نظرة على تمدد.
Let's see what happens if we change this to column.
سنغير الاتجاه المرن إلى عمود.
So align items, stretched out,
نلاحظ أن محاذاة العناصر على تمدد
we see that they're actually going to stretch across
أدت إلى تمددها
the entire width of the container that it's in.
على امتداد عرض الحاوية التي توجد فيها.
That's one of the amazing things that flex does.
وهذا إحدى الأمور المدهشة في فليكس.
If you see here, box no longer has any width and height set explicitly on it,
نلاحظ أنه لم يعد يظهر هنا عرض أو ارتفاع المربع
all it has is a border.
ويظهر عوضًا عن ذلك الحدود.
But simply by changing the way that the items are fit in to the container,
عند تغيير طريقة مواءمة العناصر داخل الحاوية،
we see them actually change their shape.
نلاحظ تغيّر شكلها.
So let's try end.
لنجرب النهاية.
So now, we have align-items end,
قمنا بمحاذاة العناصر عند النهاية.
how about align-items start? That's going to be the theme.
ماذا لو غيرنا المحاذاة عند البداية؟ لم يتغير شيء.
What if we do align-items and in a row?
ماذا لو ضبطنا محاذاة العناصر عند النهاية وفي صف؟
We'll try centered, stretch.
لنجرب توسيط وتمدد.
Let's take out justify-content.
لنستبعد ضبط المحتوى.
See what happens, no change.
نلاحظ أنه لم يتغير شيء.
What if we changed the direction of our axes?
ماذا لو غيرنا اتجاه المحاور؟
Now, we see a change.
يمكننا أن نرى تغييرًا الآن.
So you can see that align-items and justify-content act
نستنتج أن تأثير محاذاة العناصر وضبط المحتوى
differently based on the flex direction itself.
يختلف بناء على الاتجاه المرن.
Here we have one of what I think is the most comfortable setups that I use.
لدينا هنا واحدة من أكثر طرق الضبط المريحة باعتقادي
One of the things that I like to see are
فمن الأمور التي أحب أن أراها
well-distributed boxes that use up as much real estate as possible.
توزع المربعات بانتظام على أكبر قدر ممكن من المساحة
In this example, we've set up box one through five
في هذا المثال، ضبطنا المربعات من واحد إلى خمسة
to be spaced evenly throughout its parent container.
بحيث تتوزع بمسافات متساوية فيما بينها داخل الحاوية الرئيسية.
So that even if we took out,
وبهذا حتى لو حذفنا،
say box five, we can see now that
المربع الخامس مثلًا،
the four boxes will redistribute themselves to occupy the space.
ستتوزع المربعات الأربعة ثانية لتشغل المساحة.
Let's say we don't want box three anymore either,
لنقل أننا لا نريد المربع الثالث أيضًا.
you see how this works?
هل تلاحظون ماذا جرى؟
Flexbox presents a lot of magic possibilities,
يوفر «فليكس بوكس» العديد من الخيارات المذهلة،
box one, box four.
بإزالة المربع اثنان، بقي المربع واحد وأربعة
Still right in the center,
لا يزال في المنتصف تمامًا،
without any extra code,
دون الحاجة لبرمجة إضافية،
we have box one.
بقي لدينا المربع واحد.
So a lot of what we've just seen,
العديد من الأمور التي شاهدناها،
including the way that we remove and add different elements,
بما في ذلك طريقة حذف وإضافة العناصر المختلفة،
a lot of this stuff can also be done in a programming language called JavaScript.
يمكن عملها بلغة البرمجة التي تسمى جافا سكريبت.
Actually, if you look on the internet,
في الواقع، إذا بحثتم عبر الإنترنت،
there's whole sets of people who will argue
ستجدون أن العديد من الأشخاص يرون
the best way to do things because JavaScript is
أنها الطريقة الأفضل للعمل لأن جافا سكريبت
a more complex language that really allows you a dynamic possibility that CSS doesn't.
لغة أكثر تعقيدًا وتقدم لك خيارات وإمكانات حيوية لا تتوفر في CSS.
But CSS is a much simpler language that also can allow you,
ولكن CSS لغة أكثر بساطة يمكن أن تتيح لك
as you see to do some of the same things.
القيام بعدد من الأمور المماثلة.
So as you learn both of these tools,
وفيما تتعلم هاتين الأداتين،
you could weigh in on the debate about when and how to use
يمكنك الموازنة بينهما وتقرر متى وكيف تستخدم
CSS vs JavaScript to manipulate elements on your DOM.
CSS أو جافا سكريبت لترتيب العناصر في نموذج كائن المستند DOM.